(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The late, great Christopher Hitchens
الراحل العظيم "كريستوفر هيتشنز"
wrote a book called "God Is Not Great"
مؤلف كتاب "الله ليس عظيما"
whose subtitle was, "Religion Poisons Everything."
وكان عنوانه الفرعي، "الدين يسمم كل شيء."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But last month, in Time magazine,
لكن الشهر الماضي في مجلة تايم،
Rabbi David Wolpe, who I gather is referred to as America's rabbi,
الحاخام "ديفيد وولف"، و الذي اذكر انه يشار إليه بحاخام أميركا،
said, to balance that against that negative characterization,
قال، لتحقيق التوازن ضد هذا الوصف السلبي،
that no important form of social change
لا يمكن احداث تغييرات مهمه في النسيج الاجتماعي
can be brought about except through organized religion.
إلا من خلال الديانات المنظمة.
Now, remarks of this sort on the negative
الأن ,تصريحات من هذا النوع على الجانب السلبي
and the positive side are very old.
وعلى الجانب الإيجابي قديمة جدا.
I have one in my pocket here
لدي واحدة هنا في جيبي
from the first century BCE by Lucretius,
من القرن الأول قبل الميلاد من قبل "لوكريتيوس"،
the author of "On the Nature of Things," who said,
مؤلف كتاب "على طبيعة الأشياء"، الذي قال:
"Tantum religio potuit suadere malorum" --
"كان الدين قويا جدا في حضه على الشر"
I should have been able to learn that by heart —
اذ كان ينبغي علي تعلم هذا عن ظهر قلب
which is, that's how much religion
وهي ان هذه هي درجة قدرة الدين
is able to persuade people to do evil,
في التأثيرعلى البشر لاقناعهم على عمل الشر
and he was talking about the fact
وكان يتحدث عن حقيقة
of Agamemnon's decision to place his daughter
قرار "أجاممنون" لوضع ابنته
Iphigenia on an altar of sacrifice
"إيفيجينيا" على مذبح التضحية
in order to preserve the prospects of his army.
من أجل الحفاظ على آفاق جيشه.
So there have been these long debates
لذلك كانت هناك هذه المناظرات الطويلة
over the centuries, in that case, actually,
على مر القرون لذلك يمكننا في هذه الحالة
we can say over the millennia, about religion.
التحدث عن الدين لآلاف السنين
People have talked about it a lot,
وقد تحدث الناس عن الدين كثيرا،
and they've said good and bad
وذكرت أقوال جيدة و أيضا سيئة
and indifferent things about it.
وأقوال حيادية حيال ذلك.
What I want to persuade you of today
ما أريد اقناعكم به اليوم
is of a very simple claim,
هو ادعاء بسيط جدا
which is that these debates are
وهو أن هذه المناظرات هي
in a certain sense preposterous,
الى حد ما منافية للعقل،
because there is no such thing as religion
اذ أن الدين لا وجود له
about which to make these claims.
لتقديم هذه الادعاءات.
There isn't a thing called religion,
ليس هناك ما يسمى بالدين،
and so it can't be good or bad.
لذا فإنه لا يمكن أن يكون جيدا أو سيئا.
It can't even be indifferent.
لا يمكن حتى أن يكون حيادي.
And if you think about claims
وإذا فكرتم في الادعاءات
about the nonexistence of things,
حول عدم وجود الأشياء،
one obvious way to try and establish
أحد الطرق الجلية لاثبات
the nonexistence of a purported thing
عدم وجود الشيء المزعوم
would be to offer a definition of that thing
هو أولا بتقديم تعريف لهذا الشيء
and then to see whether anything satisfied it.
و من ثم نحكم اذا كان هناك ما يثبت الوجود من العدم.
I'm going to start out on that little route
سأتبع هذا المنهج من الفكر
to begin with.
لأبدأ.
So if you look in the dictionaries
إذا بحثتم في القواميس
and if you think about it,
وان فكرتم بالتعريف
one very natural definition of religion
احد التعاريف الطبيعيية للدين
is that it involves belief in gods or in spiritual beings.
هو أنه يشمل الاعتقاد بالآلهة أو بالكائنات الروحية.
As I say, this is in many dictionaries,
هذا في العديد من القواميس،
but you'll also find it actually
لكن ستجدونه ايضا
in the work of Sir Edward Tylor,
في أعمال "السير إدوارد تايلور"،
who was the first professor of anthropology at Oxford,
الذي كان أول أستاذ للالأنثروبولوجيا في أكسفورد،
one of the first modern anthropologists.
واحد من أول علماء الأنثروبولوجيا الحديثة.
In his book on primitive culture,
في كتابه عن الثقافة البدائية،
he says the heart of religion is what he called animism,
يقول: أن "الروحانية" هي عماد الدين.
that is, the belief in spiritual agency,
أي الاعتقاد في الوساطة الروحية،
The first problem for that definition
المشكلة الأولى في هذا التعريف
is from a recent novel by Paul Beatty called "Tuff."
هو من رواية حديثة أجراها "بول بيتي" تسمى "حجر بركاني".
There's a guy talking to a rabbi.
هناك رجل يتحدث الى الحاخام.
The rabbi says he doesn't believe in God.
الحاخام يقول انه لا يؤمن بالله.
The guy says, "You're a rabbi, how can you not believe in God?"
يقول الرجل: "أنت حاخام، كيف يمكنك أن لا تؤمن بالله؟"
And the reply is, "It's what's so great about being Jewish.
و الرد هو "هذا ما هو عظيم كونك يهوديا
You don't have to believe in a God per se,
اذ ليس عليك الاعتقاد بالله في حد ذاته،
just in being Jewish." (Laughter)
كونك يهوديا.
So if this guy is a rabbi, and a Jewish rabbi,
حتى إذا كان هذا الرجل هو حاخام، وحاخام اليهود،
and if you have to believe in God in order to be religious,
وكان عليك الاعتقاد بالله من أجل أن تكون متدينا،
then we have the rather counterintuitive conclusion
لذلك فسيكون لدينا الاستنتاج البديهي المناقض لفكرة الدين
that since it's possible to be a Jewish rabbi
اذ انه اذا كان من الممكن ان تكون حاخام يهودي
without believing in God,
من دون الايمان بالله
Judaism isn't a religion.
اذا اليهودية ليست ديانه.
That seems like a pretty counterintuitive thought.
استنتاج مقنع.
Here's another argument against this view.
وهنا حجة أخرى ضد هذا المنظور.
A friend of mine, an Indian friend of mine,
صديق لي و هو هندي الجنسية،
went to his grandfather when he was very young,
ذهب الى جده عندما كان صغيرا جدا،
a child, and said to him,
طفل، وقال له:
"I want to talk to you about religion,"
"أريد أن أتحدث معك عن الدين"
and his grandfather said, "You're too young.
قال له جده: "أنت صغير جدا.
Come back when you're a teenager."
عد عندما تكون في سن المراهق.
So he came back when he was a teenager,
ثم عاد اليه و هو في سن المراهقة،
and he said to his grandfather,
ثم قال لجده،
"It may be a bit late now
"قد يكون الوقت متأخرا الآن
because I've discovered that I don't believe in the gods."
لأنني اكتشفت أني لا أؤمن بالآلهة"
And his grandfather, who was a wise man, said,
وقال جده، الذي كان رجلا حكيما،
"Oh, so you belong to the atheist branch
"اذا انت تنتمي الى حزب الملحدين
of the Hindu tradition." (Laughter)
من التقاليد الهندوسية"
And finally, there's this guy,
وأخيرا، هناك هاذا الرجل،
who famously doesn't believe in God.
الذي اشتهر بعدم ايمانه بالله.
His name is the Dalai Lama.
اسمه "الدالاي لاما".
He often jokes that he's one of the world's leading atheists.
وغالبا ما يمزح بانه من قادة الملحدين في العالم.
But it's true, because the Dalai Lama's religion
ولكنه صحيح، لأن دين "الدالاي لاما"
does not involve belief in God.
لا ينطوي على الإيمان بالله.
Now you might think this just shows
الآن قد تعتقد أن هذا يوضح
that I've given you the wrong definition
إنني اعطيتك التعريف الخطأ
and that I should come up with some other definition
وأنه ينبغي علي أن آتي بتعريف مختلف
and test it against these cases
واختبره ضد هذه الحالات
and try and find something that captures
ومحاولة العثور على اي شيء قد يلتقط
atheistic Judaism, atheistic Hinduism,
الإلحادية اليهودية و الإلحادية الهندوسية،
and atheistic Buddhism as forms of religiosity,
والإلحادية البوذية كشكل من أشكال التدين،
but I actually think that that's a bad idea,
و لكنني في الواقع أعتقد أنها فكرة سيئة
and the reason I think it's a bad idea
والسبب في أنني أعتقد أنها فكرة سيئة
is that I don't think that's how
هو أنني لا أعتقد أن هذه هي الطريقة
our concept of religion works.
التي يعمل بها مفهومنا للدين.
I think the way our concept of religion works
وأعتقد أن طريقة فهمنا للدين
is that we actually have, we have a list
في الواقع هو أن لدينا قائمة
of paradigm religions
لنماذج الأديان
and their sub-parts, right,
وأجزاءها الفرعية، صحيح؟
and if something new comes along
وإذا ظهر شيء جديد
that purports to be a religion,
يدعي إنه دين،
what we ask is, "Well, is it like one of these?"
نسأل: "حسنا، هل هو مثل أي من هذه؟"
Right?
صحيح؟
And I think that's not only how we think about religion,
وأعتقد انها ليست الطريقة الوحيدة التي نفكر بها في الدين
and that's, as it were,
وهذا، كما كان،
so from our point of view,
من وجهة نظرنا،
anything on that list had better be a religion,
أي شيء على تلك القائمة يستحسن ان يكون ديانه
which is why I don't think an account of religion
لذلك لا اعتقد أي ديانه
that excludes Buddhism and Judaism
تستبعد البوذية و اليهودية
has a chance of being a good starter,
لديها الفرصة لتأخذ بعين الاعتبار،
because they're on our list.
لأنهم على قائمتنا.
But why do we have such a list?
ولكن لماذا لدينا هذه القائمة؟
What's going on? How did it come about
ماذا يحدث هنا؟ ما الذي أدى الى أن
that we have this list?
يكون لدينا هذه القائمة؟
I think the answer is a pretty simple one
أعتقد أن الجواب بسيط جدا
and therefore crude and contentious.
و هو بالتالي حاد ومثير للجدل.
I'm sure a lot of people will disagree with it,
أنا متأكد أن الكثير لن يتفقوا مع هذا الأمر
but here's my story,
لكن اليكم حكايتي،
and true or not, it's a story that I think
سواءا أكانت صحيحه أم لا انها الحكاية التي أعتقد
gives you a good sense of how
انها ستمنحكم شعور جيد عن كيفية
the list might have come about,
ظهور هذه القائمة.
and therefore helps you to think about
بالتالي تساعدكم على التفكير
what use the list might be.
باستخدامات هذه القائمة.
I think the answer is, European travelers,
أعتقد أن الجواب هو، الرحالة الأوروبيين،
starting roughly about the time of Columbus,
بدء تقريبا في عصر "كولومبوس"،
started going around the world.
بدأو بالترحال الى انحاء العالم
They came from a Christian culture,
جاءوا من ثقافة مسيحية،
and when they arrived in a new place,
وعندما وصلوا إلى مكان جديد،
they noticed that some people didn't have Christianity,
لاحظوا أن بعض الناس لا تتبع المسيحية،
and so they asked themselves the following question:
فسألوا أنفسهم السؤال التالي:
what have they got instead of Christianity?
ماذا لديهم عوضا عن المسيحية؟
And that list was essentially constructed.
و تم انشاء تلك القائمة.
It consists of the things that other people had
و تتألف من الأشياء التي يعتقدها الآخرين
instead of Christianity.
بدلا عن المسيحية.
Now there's a difficulty with proceeding in that way,
الان هناك صعوبة بالاستمرار على هذا النحو
which is that Christianity is extremely,
وهو أن المسيحية لها و بشكل مفرط،
even on that list, it's an extremely specific tradition.
حتى في تلك القائمة، تقاليد محدده للغاية.
It has all kinds of things in it
تحتوي على جميع أنواع الأشياء
that are very, very particular
التي هي محددة جدا
that are the results of the specifics
والتي هي نتائج تفاصيل
of Christian history,
من التاريخ المسيحي،
and one thing that's at the heart of it,
والفكرة الأساسية في المسيحية،
one thing that's at the heart of most understandings of Christianity,
والفكرة الأساسية في غالبية المفاهيم المسيحية،
which is the result of the specific history of Christianity,
و هو نتيجة التاريخ المسيحي المحدد.
is that it's an extremely creedal religion.
هو أنه دين عقائدي للغاية.
It's a religion in which people are really concerned
انه دين، فيه الناس قلقون
about whether you believe the right things.
حول ما إذا كنت تؤمن بالأمور الصحيحة.
The history of Christianity, the internal history of Christianity,
تاريخ المسيحية، و التاريخ الداخلي للمسيحية،
is largely the history of people killing each other
إلى حد كبير تاريخ قتل الناس بعضهم البعض
because they believed the wrong thing,
لأنهم آمنوا بالشيء الخطأ،
and it's also involved in
و انها تضمنت أيضا
struggles with other religions,
صراعات مع الأديان الأخرى،
obviously starting in the Middle Ages,
ابتداءا من العصور الوسطى،
a struggle with Islam,
الصراع مع الاسلام،
in which, again, it was the infidelity,
كان الموضوع ,للمرة الثانية, كان التكفير
the fact that they didn't believe the right things,
كفروهم لأنهم لم يؤمنوا بالأمور الصحيحة.
that seemed so offensive to the Christian world.
والتي بدت مسيئة جدا للعالم المسيحي.
Now that's a very specific and particular history
هذا تاريخ محدد جدا
that Christianity has,
للمسيحية،
and not everywhere is everything
اذ لم يسبق أن
that has ever been put on this sort of list like it.
تم وضع أي شيء على هذا النوع من القوائم كالمسيحية.
Here's another problem, I think.
اليكم مشكلة أخرى على ما أعتقد.
A very specific thing happened.
حدث شيء مميز جدا.
It was actually adverted to earlier,
و تم الاشاره اليه في وقت سابق،
but a very specific thing happened
لكن حدث شيء مميز جدا.
in the history of the kind of Christianity
في تاريخ نوع المسيحية
that we see around us
الذي نراه من حولنا
mostly in the United States today,
غالبا في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية اليوم
and it happened in the late 19th century,
وحدث في أواخر القرن التاسع عشر،
and that specific thing that happened
و الشيء المميز الذي حدث
in the late 19th century
أواخر القرن التاسع عشر
was a kind of deal that was cut
كان نوعا من الاتفاق الذي تم عقده
between science,
بين العلم
this new way of organizing intellectual authority,
هذه الطريقة الجديدة لتنظيم السلطة الفكرية،
and religion.
و الدين.
If you think about the 18th century, say,
إذا تفكرت في القرن الثامن عشر، لنقل
if you think about intellectual life
اذا تفكرت بالحياة الفكرية
before the late 19th century,
ما قبل القرن الثامن عشر،
anything you did, anything you thought about,
أي شيء قمت به، أي شيء فكرت به،
whether it was the physical world,
سواء كان ذلك العالم المادي،
the human world,
العالم البشري،
the natural world apart from the human world,
العالم الطبيعي بعيدا عن العالم البشري،
or morality, anything you did
أو الأخلاق، أي شيء فعلته
would have been framed against the background
سيتم ارجاعه الى
of a set of assumptions that were religious,
مجموعة من الافتراضات الدينية،
Christian assumptions.
افتراضات دينية مسيحية.
You couldn't give an account
لا يمكنك أن تقدم بياناً عن
of the natural world
العالم الطبيعي
that didn't say something about its relationship,
اذا ما ذكر شيئا عن علاقته،
for example, to the creation story
على سبيل المثال، بقصة الخلق
in the Abrahamic tradition,
في التقاليد الإبراهيمية،
the creation story in the first book of the Torah.
قصة الخلق في الكتاب الأول من التوراة.
So everything was framed in that way.
لذلك كل شيء تم نسجه بهاذا الأسلوب.
But this changes in the late 19th century,
لكن تغير هذا في أواخر القرن التاسع عشر.
and for the first time, it's possible for people
وللمرة الأولى، اصبح ممكنا للناس
to develop serious intellectual careers
تطوير المهن الفكرية
as natural historians like Darwin.
كمؤرخ للطبيعة مثل "داروين"
Darwin worried about the relationship between
قلق داروين حول العلاقة بين
what he said and the truths of religion,
ما قاله و الحقائق الدينية،
but he could proceed, he could write books
لكن أمكنه المضي قدما و كتابة المؤلفات
about his subject
حول موضوعه
without having to say what the relationship was
دون الحاجة إلى توضيح العلاقة تجاه
to the religious claims,
الادعاءات الدينية،
and similarly, geologists increasingly could talk about it.
اذ تمكن للجيولوجيين أيضا التحدث وبشكل متزايد
In the early 19th century, if you were a geologist
لو كنت جيولوجيا أوائل القرن التاسع عشر
and made a claim about the age of the Earth,
وقدمت ادعاء حول عمر الأرض،
you had to explain whether that was consistent
كان عليك توضيح ما إذا كان ذلك يتفق
or how it was or wasn't consistent
أو كيف يتفق أو لا يتفق
with the age of the Earth implied
ضمنيا مع عمر الأرض
by the account in Genesis.
في كتاب سفر التكوين.
By the end of the 19th century,
بنهاية القرن التاسع عشر.
you can just write a geology textbook
أمكنك تأليف كتاب في الجيولوجيا
in which you make arguments about how old the Earth is.
و تقديم الحجج عن قدم الأرض
So there's a big change, and that division,
إذا هناك تغيير كبير و هذا الانقسام
that intellectual division of labor occurs as I say, I think,
هذا الانقسام الفكري للعمل يحدث بينما أتكلم، و هذا باعتقادي
and it sort of solidifies so that by the end
و نوعا ما في رسوخ حتى أنه بحلول نهاية
of the 19th century in Europe,
القرن التاسع عشر في أوروبا،
there's a real intellectual division of labor,
هناك انقسام فكري حقيقي في العمل،
and you can do all sorts of serious things,
و يمكنك أن تفعل كل أنواع الأشياء المهمة،
including, increasingly, even philosophy,
بما في ذلك، على نحو متزايد، الفلسفة،
without being constrained by the thought,
دون تقيد الفكر حيال،
"Well, what I have to say has to be consistent
"حسنا، ماذا يجب أن أقول حتى تكون متوافقة
with the deep truths that are given to me
مع الحقائق العميقة التي اعطيت لي
by our religious tradition."
من خلال تقاليدنا الدينية."
So imagine someone who's coming out
لذا تخيل ان أحدا قادم من
of that world, that late-19th-century world,
ذلك العالم، من أواخر القرن التاسع عشر
coming into the country that I grew up in, Ghana,
قادم الى البلاد التي نشأت فيها "غانا"
the society that I grew up in, Asante,
والمجتمع الذي نشأت فيه "أشانتي"
coming into that world
يأتي الى ذلك العالم
at the turn of the 20th century
في مطلع القرن العشرين
with this question that made the list:
مع هذا السؤال الذي صنع القائمة:
what have they got instead of Christianity?
ماذا لديهم بدلا عن المسيحية؟
Well, here's one thing he would have noticed,
حسنا، هذا شيء كان ليلاحظه،
and by the way, there was a person who actually did this.
و بالمناسبة، هناك من فعل ذلك.
His name was Captain Rattray,
اسمه "الكابتن راتراي"،
he was sent as the British government anthropologist,
بعثته الحكومة البريطانية كعالم انثروبولوجيا
and he wrote a book about Asante religion.
وكتب كتابا عن ديانة "اشانتي".
This is a soul disc.
"اسطوانة الروح".
There are many of them in the British Museum.
وهناك العديد منها في المتحف البريطاني.
I could give you an interesting, different history
استطيع ان احكي تاريخ شيق ومختلف
of how it comes about that many of the things
عن كيفية وصول الكثير من تراث
from my society ended up in the British Museum,
مجتمعي الى المتحف البريطاني،
but we don't have time for that.
ولكن ليس لدينا الوقت لذلك.
So this object is a soul disc.
اذا هذا الشيء هو أسطوانة الروح.
What is a soul disc?
ما هي أسطوانة الروح؟
It was worn around the necks
كانت توضع حول أعناق
of the soul-washers of the Asante king.
غاسلي الأرواح لدى ملك الأشانتي.
What was their job? To wash the king's soul.
ما هي وظيفتهم؟ غسل روح الملك.
It would take a long while
يستغرق الأمر فترة طويلة
to explain how a soul could be the kind of thing
لشرح كيف أن الروح هي عبارة عن شيء
that could be washed,
يمكن غسله،
but Rattray knew that this was religion
ولكن "راتراي" علم أن هذا هو الدين.
because souls were in play.
لأن الأرواح كانت جزء من ذلك.
And similarly,
وعلى نحو مماثل،
there were many other things, many other practices.
كانت هناك العديد من الأشياء و الممارسات الأخرى.
For example, every time anybody had a drink, more or less,
على سبيل المثال، في كل مرة يحتسي احدهم الخمر
they poured a little bit on the ground
يقوم بسكب القليل منه على الأرض
in what's called the libation,
هذا ما يسمى بإراقة الخمر،
and they gave some to the ancestors.
ويوفروا القليل للأجداد.
My father did this. Every time he opened a bottle of whiskey,
والدي فعل هذا. في كل مرة يفتح فيها زجاجة ويسكي،
which I'm glad to say was very often,
و سعيد أن أقول غالبا ما كان يفعل،
he would take the top off and pour off just a little on the ground,
كان يفتح الزجاجة و يسكب القليل على الأرض
and he would talk to,
و كان يتكلم مع,
he would say to Akroma-Ampim, the founder of our line,
كان يقول انه يتكل مع "أكروما أمبم" المؤسس.
or Yao Antony, my great uncle,
أو "ياو أنتوني"، عمي الكبير،
he would talk to them,
كان يتكلم معهم،
offer them a little bit of this.
يقدم لهم بعض الشراب.
And finally, there were these huge public ceremonials.
وأخيرا، كان هناك الاحتفالات الضخمة العامة. هذا
This is an early-19th-century drawing
رسم من أوائل القرن التاسع عشر
by another British military officer
بواسطة عسكري بريطاني آخر
of such a ceremonial,
لهذه المراسم،
where the king was involved,
حيث شارك الملك،
and the king's job,
و كان عمل الملك،
one of the large parts of his job,
وأحد أهم أجزاء وظيفته،
apart from organizing warfare and things like that,
بعيدا عن تنظيم الحرب وأشياء من هذا القبيل،
was to look after the tombs of his ancestors,
هو رعاية مقابر أجداده،
and when a king died,
و عندما يموت الملك،
the stool that he sat on was blackened
يتم تسويد مقعده
and put in the royal ancestral temple,
ويوضع في معبد الأجداد الملكي،
and every 40 days,
و كل اربعين يوما،
the King of Asante has to go and do cult
يذهب ملك الأشانتي للقيام بطقوس العبادة
for his ancestors.
لأسلافه.
That's a large part of his job,
وهذا أحد أهم أجزاء وظيفته،
and people think that if he doesn't do it,
والناس يعتقدون أنه إذا لم يفعل ذلك،
things will fall apart.
ستنهار الأمور.
So he's a religious figure,
اذا هو شخصية دينية،
as Rattray would have said,
كما كان سيقول "راتراي"،
as well as a political figure.
وأيضا كشخصية سياسية.
So all this would count as religion for Rattray,
لذلك كل هذا كان يعتبر من الدين بالنسبه ل"راتراي"،
but my point is that when you look
لكن وجهة نظري هي أنه عندما تنظر
into the lives of those people,
في حياة هؤلاء الناس،
you also find that every time they do anything,
تجد أيضا أنه في كل مرة يفعلون أي شيء،
they're conscious of the ancestors.
يتواصلون مع أسلافهم.
Every morning at breakfast,
كل صباح عند وجبة الإفطار،
you can go outside the front of the house
يمكنك الخروج امام منزلك
and make an offering to the god tree, the nyame dua
وأن تقدم قربانا الى شجرة الله "نايام دوها"
outside your house,
خارج منزلك،
and again, you'll talk to the gods
وعليك التحدث إلى الآلهة
and the high gods and the low gods
الآلهة العليا والدنيا
and the ancestors and so on.
و الأجداد و إلى آخره.
This is not a world
هذا ليس عالم
in which the separation between religion and science
حيث الفصل بين العلم والدين
has occurred.
قد تم فيه.
Religion has not being separated
لم يتم فصل الدين
from any other areas of life,
عن أي مجالات الحياة الأخرى
and in particular,
وعلى وجه الخصوص،
what's crucial to understand about this world
وما هو ضروري فهمه حول هذا العالم
is that it's a world in which the job
هو أنه عالم حيث المهمة
that science does for us
التي يقدمها لنا العلم
is done by what Rattray is going to call religion,
يتم انجازها من خلال ما يسميه "راتراي" بالدين.
because if they want an explanation of something,
لأنه عندما يريدوا تفسيرا لشيء ما،
if they want to know why the crop just failed,
اذا أرادوا معرفة سبب فشل الزراعة،
if they want to know why it's raining
اذا أرادوا تعليل هطول المطر
or not raining, if they need rain,
أو تعليل عدم هطول المطر إذا كانوا بحاجة لمطر
if they want to know why
اذا أرادوا تعليل
their grandfather has died,
موت جدهم،
they are going to appeal to the very same entities,
سوف يستغيثون بنفس الكيانات،
the very same language,
و بنفس اللغة،
talk to the very same gods about that.
و نفس الآلهة عن السبب.
This great separation, in other words,
هذا الفصل العظيم، وبعبارة أخرى،
between religion and science hasn't happened.
بين الدين والعلم لم يحدث.
Now, this would be a mere historical curiosity,
الآن، سيكون هذا مجرد فضول تاريخي،
except that in large parts of the world,
إلا أنه في أجزاء واسعة من العالم،
this is still the truth.
ما زال حقيقة.
I had the privilege of going to a wedding
كان لي شرف الذهاب الى حفل زفاف
the other day in northern Namibia,
في احد الأيام في شمال "ناميبيا"،
20 miles or so south of the Angolan border
عشرين ميلا أو نحو ذلك إلى الجنوب من الحدود "الأنغولية"
in a village of 200 people.
في قرية مكونة من مئتي شخص.
These were modern people.
هؤلاء أشخاص متحضرون.
We had with us Oona Chaplin,
كان معنا "أونا شابلن"،
who some of you may have heard of,
قد سمع البعض منكم عنها.
and one of the people from this village came up to her,
أحد سكان هذه القرية اتى اليها
and said, "I've seen you in 'Game of Thrones.'"
وقال: لقد رأيتك في" لعبة العروش".
So these were not people who were isolated from our world,
لذلك لم يكن هؤلاء الأشخاص معزولون عن عالمنا
but nevertheless, for them,
لكن، بالنسبة لهم،
the gods and the spirits are still very much there,
الآلهه و الأرواح ما زالت موجوده،
and when we were on the bus going back and forth
وعندما كنا نتنقل في الحافلة
to the various parts of the [ceremony],
الى أجزاء مختلفة من الحفل،
they prayed not just in a generic way
صلوا وليس فقط بطريقة عامة
but for the safety of the journey,
ولكن من أجل سلامة الرحلة،
and they meant it,
و قد عنوا ذلك،
and when they said to me that my mother,
عندما قالوا لي أن والدتي،
the bridegroom's [grandmother],
جدة العريس،
was with us, they didn't mean it figuratively.
كانت معنا، لم يكن هذا تعبير مجازي.
They meant, even though she was a dead person,
القصد، على الرغم من أنها ميته
they meant that she was still around.
لكنها لا تزال موجوده في الأرجاء.
So in large parts of the world today,
لذا في أجزاء كبيرة من العالم اليوم
that separation between science and religion
هذا الفصل بين العلم والدين
hasn't occurred in large parts of the world today,
لم يحدث في أجزاء كبيرة من العالم
and as I say, these are not --
كما قلت، عم ليسوا منهم
This guy used to work for Chase and at the World Bank.
هذا الرجل كان يعمل في "تشيس" و في "البنك الدولي".
These are fellow citizens of the world with you,
هؤلاء زملاؤكم من العالم هنا معكم
but they come from a place in which religion
لكنهم قدموا من مكان حيث الدين
is occupying a very different role.
يحتل دورا مختلفا تماما.
So what I want you to think about next time somebody wants
لذا ما أريدكم التفكير فيه في حال اراد شخص
to make some vast generalization about religion
اجراء تعميم واسع عن الدين
is that maybe there isn't such a thing
هو أنه ربما لا يوجد شيء
as a religion, such a thing as religion,
ما يسمى بالدين
and that therefore what they say
وبالتالي ما يقولون
cannot possibly be true.
لا يمكن أن يكون صحيحا.